Guide to the Montana Legislative Assembly (35th: 1957) records 1957
Montana Historical Society
Montana Legislative Assembly (35th: 1957) records
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 35
Montana. Legislative Assembly.
2 linear feet of shelf space
Collection contains the records (1957) of the Montana 35th Legislative Assembly including the minutes and reports of House and Senate standing committees; House and Senate bills, resolutions, memorials, and joint resolutions and memorials; and miscellany.
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 35th Montana Legislature met from January 7th to March 7th, 1957. The leaders of the Senate were Paul Cannon (D-President), David James (D-President Pro Tempore), David James (D-Majority Leader), and Donovan Worden (R-Minority Leader). The leaders of the House were Eugene Mahoney (D-Speaker), John MacDonald (D-Speaker Pro Tempore), Fred Barrett (D-Majority Leader), and R.F. Juedeman (R-Minority Leader).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
The collection includes the minutes and reports of House and Senate standing committees; House and Senate bills, and resolutions; House Memorials (re increased production of wheat grown for federal farm programs; erection of a custom smelter to eliminate overcharges to independent mines; high frequency television translators; and construction of a sign near Frontier Town); Senate Memorials (re adjustment in federal farm program relating to growing of quality wheat); and House and Senate joint memorials. The collection also contains miscellany material including a report of the House Select Committee Appointed to Investigate the Milk Control Board; and exhibits regarding public welfare act and "Oil Progress Week" Program.
The collection is organized into four series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany.
The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into one subseries, Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically).
The series House of Representatives is organized into eight subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), House Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), House Memorials (arranged numerically by bill number), House Joint Memorials (arranged numerically by bill number), Status Sheets of House Bills (arranged chronologically), and House Memorial Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number).
The series Senate is organized into five subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Memorials (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Joint Memorials (arranged numerically by bill number), and Senate Confirmation Resolutions (arranged chronologically).
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Montana--Committees.
Libby Dam (Mont.); Montana--Politics and government.; Paradise Dam (Mont.)
Montana.; Government and olitics.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- House and Senate Joint Committees
  - Joint Committee Minutes
    - [See Joint House Agriculture Committee minutes in Senate Agriculture Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint Appropriations and Senate Finance Claims Subcommittee minutes in House Appropriations Committee and Senate Finance and Claims Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint Conference Committee on County Affairs minutes in Senate County Affairs Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint House and Senate Education Committee Hearing on H.B. 127 in Senate Education Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint Indian Affairs Committee Hearing on H.J. Memorial 6, 14, and 15; and S.J. Memorial 5 in Senate Indian Affairs Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint Irrigation and Water Conservation Committee minutes in Senate Irrigation and Water Conservation Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint Irrigation and Water Conservation Committee Hearing on Paradise Dam Project in Senate Irrigation and Water Conservation Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint Conference Committee on Public Health and Safety minutes in Senate Public Health and Safety Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint Relief and Social Security Committee minutes in Senate Relief and Social Security Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint State Boards, Offices and Building Committee Hearing on H.B. 452 in Senate Boards, Offices and Committee Minutes]
- House of Representatives
  - House Standing Committee Minutes
    - Affairs of Cities, 1957 January 28 - February 27 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Agriculture, Dairying and Horticulture, 1957 January 14 - March 5 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - Appropriations (includes Joint House Appropriations and Senate Finance and Claims Subcommittee, January 18- March 1, 1957), 1957 January 9 - March 7 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - Banking and Insurance, 1957 January 22 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Conservation and Development, 1957 February 8 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Constitutional Amendments and Federal Relations, 1957 January 24 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Education, 1957 January 18 - March 4 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Employment, 1957 January 7 - February 6 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - Fish and Game, 1957 January 27 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - Highways and Highway Transportation, 1957 January 16 - March 4 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Intergovernmental Cooperation, 1957 January 29 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
    - Irrigation and Water Conservation, 1957 January 16 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Judiciary, 1957 January 18 - March 2 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
    - Labor, 1957 January 17 - February 19 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
    - Liquor Control, 1957 January 24 - February 14 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
    - Livestock and Public Ranges, 1957 January 22 - February 19 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
    - Military Affairs, 1957 January 18 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
    - Mines and Mining, 1957 February 13-18 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
    - Oil and Gas, 1957 January 21 - March 5 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
    - Privileges and Elections, 1957 January 28 - February 13 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
    - Public Health, Morals and Safety, 1957 January 22 - February 28 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
    - Public Utilities and State Commissions, 1957 February 6 - March 1 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
    - Railway and Aviation Transportation, 1957 January 30 - February 25 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
    - Social Security, 1957 January 23 - February 27 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
    - State Boards and Institutions, 1957 January 23 - February 27 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
    - State Lands, Forests and Parks, 1957 January 25 - February 15 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
    - Townships and Counties, 1957 January 17 - February 28 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
    - Ways and Means, 1957 January 22 - March 2 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
    - Workmen's Compensation, 1957 January 18 - March 1 (Box-folder 1 / 29)
  - House Bills
    - Bill nos. 1-420, 1957 (Box-folder 1 / 30-40)
    - Bill nos. 421-481, 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 1-3)
  - House Resolutions
    - Bill no. 6, 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - House Joint Resolutions
    - Bill nos. 1-3, 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - House Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-4 (re increased production of wheat grown for federal farm programs; erection of a custom smelter to eliminate overcharges to independent mines; high frequency television translators; and construction of a sign near Frontier Town), 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - House Joint Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-19 (re construction of Paradise Dam; investigation of beef prices; construction of Libby Dam; construction of Yellowstone Dam; increasing personal income tax credit exemption; effects of off-reservation migration on American Indians; public hearing to adjust railroad freight rates; construction of Glacier view Dam; power generation on the Missouri River; establishing the pound weight as the unit of measure in grain trade; continuing experimental wheat in allotted acreage for each farm; use of federal power in the Missouri River Basin; transmountain diversion of the Middle Fork of the Flathead River; federal responsibility to Indian people; purchase of coal from the Tongue River Indian Reservation; construction of Lewis and Clark Highway; free marketing of newly mined gold; state jurisdiction over criminal and civil matters on Indian reservations; and soil conservation practices on placer claims), 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Status Sheets of House Bills
    - 2nd - 54th Legislative Days, 1957 January 8 - March 1 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - House Memorial Resolutions
    - Necrology Committee, 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
- Senate
  - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
    - Agriculture (includes Joint Senate and House Agriculture committees, February 11, 1957), 1957 January 17 - March 6 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - Banks and Banking, 1957 January 17 - February 13 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
    - City and Town Affairs, 1957 January 18 - March 2 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
    - Committee on Committee, 1957 January 8 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
    - Constitutional Amendments and Federal Relations, 1957 February 28 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
    - County Affairs (includes Joint House and Senate Conference Committee on County Affairs, February 28, 1957), 1957 January 21 - February 28 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
    - Education (includes Joint Hearing on H.B. 127 regarding equalization of financial distribution for schools, February 16, 1957), 1957 January 23 - March 11 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
    - Election and Apportionment, 1957 February 5-15 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
    - Finance and Claims (includes Joint House Appropriations and Senate Finance and Claims Committee, February 18, 1957), 1957 January 9 - March 7 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
    - Fish and Game, 1957 January 22 - March 2 (Box-folder 2 / 19)
    - Highways and Transportation, 1957 January 24 - March 4 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
    - Indian Affairs (includes Joint House and Senate Indian Affairs Committee hearing, February 7, 1957), 1957 January 22 - February 26 (Box-folder 2 / 21)
    - Insurance, 1957 January 30 - February 12 (Box-folder 2 / 22)
    - Inter-Governmental Cooperation, 1957 February 11-26 (Box-folder 2 / 23)
    - Irrigation and Water Conservation (includes Joint House and Senate Irrigation and Water Conservation committees, January 16, 1957; and Joint Hearing on Paradise Dam Project, January 26, 1957), 1957 January 16 - March 3 (Box-folder 2 / 24)
    - Judiciary, 1957 January 29 - March 4 (Box-folder 2 / 25)
    - Labor and Compensation, 1957 January 24 - March 2 (Box-folder 2 / 26)
    - Liquor Control, 1957 January 18 - February 27 (Box-folder 2 / 27)
    - Military Affairs, 1957 February 1-13 (Box-folder 2 / 28)
    - Mines and Mining, 1957 January 6 - February 14 (Box-folder 2 / 29)
    - Oil and Leases, 1957 January 30 - February 25 (Box-folder 2 / 30)
    - Public Health and Safety (includes Joint Conference Committee on H.B. 107 regarding barber schools and colleges charging for services, March 5, 1957), 1957 January 24 - March 5 (Box-folder 2 / 31)
    - Public Lands, 1957 January 22 - February 19 (Box-folder 2 / 32)
    - Public Utilities and Industry, 1957 January 31 - March 2 (Box-folder 2 / 33)
    - Relief and Social Security (includes Joint House and Senate Relief and Social Security committees, February 1, 1957), 1957 January 25 - March 2 (Box-folder 2 / 34)
    - State Boards, Offices and Buildings (includes Joint Hearing on H.B. 452 regarding Charlie Russell statue, February 16, 1957; and confirmation resolutions), 1957 January 21 - March 7 (Box-folder 2 / 35)
    - Stockgrowing and Grazing, 1957 January 24 - March 2 (Box-folder 2 / 36)
    - Taxation, 1957 January 7 - March 4 (Box-folder 2 / 37)
  - Senate Bills
    - Bill nos. 1-150, 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 38-40)
    - Bill nos. 151-223, 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 41-42)
  - Senate Memorials
    - Bill no. 2 (re adjustment in federal farm program relating to growing of quality wheat), 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 43)
  - Senate Joint Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-8 (re control of grasshoppers on range and grazing lands; use of federal income tax for educational funds; collection of sales tax in Yellowstone Park by Wyoming; diversion of water from the Madison River; promoting employment of Indian citizens near reservations; G.I. loan interest rates; stock piling domestic tungsten for defense purposes; and downstream power installation charges for benefits derived from upstream power projects), 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 44)
  - Senate Confirmation Resolutions
    - [see Confirmation resolutions in Senate State Boards, Offices and Buildings Committee minutes]
- Miscellany
  - Exhibits regarding public welfare act and "Oil Progress Week" Program, 1953, 1956 (Box-folder 2 / 45)
  - Report of the House Select Committee Appointed to Investigate the Milk Control Board, 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 46)
  - Seating Chart, 1957 (Box-folder 2 / 47)